A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Corporation, Board of Trustees, Secretary FA859
Rockefeller Archive Center
As the changing character of the Institute evolved, By-Laws were amended, Resolutions were rescinded and changes were instituted to provide for the development of the Institute along the lines suggested by the Report of the Committee on Nomination and Review. To the three committees originally provided in the By-Laws was added an elected Committee on Audit. Added also were appointive committees: Committee on Educational Policies, Committee on Research, Committee on Business Operations, Committee on Buildings and Grounds and a Committee on Nominations. January 30, 1957 a Committee on Hospital Affairs was appointed to review present and future hospital policies.
In 1955, Thomas M. Rivers, Vice-President and Director of the Institute retired and at that time resolutions were taken to discontinue the division of the Institute into Departments, to eliminate the position of Director of the Institute and to provide for several Vice-Presidents, Frank L. Horsfall served as Vice-President for Clinical Studies 1955-1957 and Douglas Whitaker was Vice-President for Administration 1955-1964. When Edric Smith retired in 1955, John E. Lockwood then Assistant Counsel became, in addition, Secretary of the Board and after the death in 1958 of Thomas Debevoise he became in 1959 both Secretary and Counsel.
New members of the Board of Trustees were: in 1954, Robert Loeb, Eli Whitney Debevoise, Kenneth C. Brownell (1954-1958); in 1956, William J. Robbins; in 1957, Philip Bard; in 1958, Albert L. Nickerson; in 1960, J. Richardson Dilworth and William O. Baker; in 1961 Baron Edgar Douglas Adrian; in 1966 George F. Bennett and Frederick Seitz; in 1968, Philip Handler and John W. Gardner; in 1969, Thomas Grady Cousins, Walter N. Rothschild, Jr., Robert Gregg Stone and Chauncey William Wallace Cook; in 1970, Christian Archibald Herter, Jr. Resignations from the Board of Trustees were: in 1954, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.; 1955, Thomas M. Rivers; 1957 Ross Granville Harrison; 1959 John C. Traphagen and Alphonse Raymond Dochez; 1964 George Murnane; 1965 Baron Edgar Douglas Adrian; 1966 William J. Robbins and Barklie McKee Henry died in 1966.
George H. Whipple who had served on the Board of Scientific Directors and been their elected representative on the Board of Trustees and its Vice-President became a member of the newly constituted Board of Trustees in 1953. He was elected Vice-Chairman and held that office until his resignation in October 1960. Robert F. Loeb was then elected Vice-Chairman of the Board where he served until he resigned May 1970 and was succeeded by William O. Baker.
Changes in Charter and By-Laws were made as the changes in Institute organization developed. In May 1965 the Corporate name was changed to The Rockefeller University and the new Charter and amended By-Laws were published in 1966. They provided that the number of Trustees be between five and twenty-five; that elected officers be a Chairman, Vice-Chairman, and a President all of whom shall be or become Trustees. Other elected officers were to be Secretary and Treasurer, one or more Vice-Presidents, Assistant Secretaries and Assistant Treasurers and other officers as considered necessary by the Board. One person may be elected to more than one office except that President and Secretary may not be the same person. Officers are elected for one year or until respective successors are elected.
On the retirement of Detlev Bronk (who became a Trustee Emeritus) in October 1968, Frederick Seitz was elected President; C. Eugene Sunderlin was elected to succeed John E. Lockwood as Secretary at the time of Mr. Lockwood's retirement and Donal C. O'Brien, Jr. became Counsel at that time.
Board changes:
Additions: Bearn, Alexander G. 1970; Hildebrand, John G. 1970; Kac, Mark 1970; Yang, Chen Ning 1970; Bassine, Charles C. 1971; Casimir, Hendrik E.G. 1971; Haggerty, Patrick E. 1971; Heiskell, Marion S. 1971; Rockefeller, David, Jr. 1971; Whitehead, Edwin C. 1971; Linen, James A. III 1972; Astor, Brooke (Mrs. Vincent Astor) 1972
Retirements or Resignations: David, Donald K. 1971; Gardner, John W. 1971; Kimball, Lindsley 1971; Cook, Chauncey William W. 1972
Resignation: Kac, Mark 1973; Hildebrand, John G. 1973
Additions: Griffin, Donald R. 1973; Williams, Robley C. Jr. 1973
Additions: Ralph E. Ablon 1974; Nicholas F. Brady 1974
In October of 1975 David Rockefeller resigned as Chairman of the Board of Trustees and became Chairman of the Trustees' Executive Committee in order to concentrate his attention on the University's program to broaden its base of private support. He was succeeded as Chairman of the Board by Patrick E. Haggerty.
New Board appointments: Dr. Lewis Thomas 1975; Dr. Seymour S. Kety 1976; Mrs. Anne E. Reed 1976; Dr. P. Roy Vagelos 1976; Richard M. Furlaud 1976; John R. Stevenson 1976; Neva Rockefeller Kaiser 1977; Norman F. Ramsey 1977; Alexander D. Forger 1978; J. Paul Sticht 1978; Frank T. Cary 1978; Pamela Harriman 1979; David A. Hamburg 1979; Curtis L. Blake 1980
Retirements: resignations: Philip Bard 1974-1975; David Rockefeller, Jr. 1977; Patrick E Haggerty died suddenly October 1, 1980; William O. Baker elected Chairman of Bd. of Trustees October 21, 1980
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of the RAC.
Scope and Contents
Contains files of Starr Murphy, Raymond Fosdick, Trevor Arnett and Edric Smith.
- Starr J. Murphy (1911-1921); Raymond B. Fosdick (1921-1936); Trevor Arnett (1936); Edric B. Smith (1936-1955), 1910-1955; 4 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Administrative papers and correspondence.
  The kinds of material included varies greatly depending upon who filled the office of Secretary of the Board of Trustees but in general deals with the business of the Trustees in maintaining and developing Institute properties and appointments. Includes correspondence with Trustees, Officers, and Business Manager. Items from the Director of the Institute to be placed on Docket for meetings. Preliminary drafts of Minutes of meetings and Resolutions. Includes notices of nominations made by the Board of Scientific Directors to fill vacancies in the membership of the Scientific Directors.
  Includes some preliminary dockets, or dockets and some notices of meetings and invitations also including some proxies and replies.
  From 1944 some original signed approvals of actions of the Executive Committee.
  Originals of action on budget signed by Budget Committee for the years of 1925/1926, 1926/1927, 1927/1928, 1930/1931, 1932/1933.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged in chronological order.
  - 1910-1926 (Box 1)
    - Items of interest include: (Box 1)
      - Notice of special meeting June 12, 1911 signed by Starr J. Murphy to adopt new article to the Trustees' Rules to provide for a Finance Committee, 1911 May 31 (Box 1)
      - Report to Board of Trustees from Committee (Henry James, Starr J. Murphy, Jerome D. Greene) on Fire risk and suggested coverage (Committee on Insurance), 1916 February 3 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence concerning laboratory of Social Hygiene, Bedford Hills, NY - Miss Davis; Mabel R. Fernald, 1913-1915 (Box 1)
      - Letter from Starr J. Murphy to Henry James stating that formal authorizations of budgets be filed with Minute Book, 1916 April 27 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence between Starr J. Murphy and Simon Flexner dealing with plans for an international commission to study tuberculosis as an activity of the Rockefeller Foundation including a projected compilation of funds required for Rockefeller Foundation activities 1916-1921 (dated December 7, 1916), 1916 November 6[?]-15 (Box 1)
      - To Henry James from Starr J. Murphy regarding use of name of Institute in advertisements of Duffy Malt Whiskey Company recommending use of whiskey in treatment of diabetes, 1916 November 22 (Box 1)
      - Hand written report on war activities by Simon Flexner for submission to Rockefeller Foundation, 1918 July 1 (Box 1)
      - Handwritten letter from William Welch accepting election as Vice-president of Corporation, 1922 January 27 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence between L.G. Myers, Treasurer, F.T. Gates, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Raymond Fosdick, Secretary on revising manner of composition and operation of Finance Committee to avoid possible accusation of tax evasion. Four page handwritten letter by F.T. Gates explaining his stand, 1923 December 3-1924 February 7 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence between F.T. Gates, Bertram Cutler, Simon Flexner and Raymond Fosdick regarding F.T. Gates resignation from Finance Committee and Institute Board, 1925 December 19-1926 January 26 (Box 1)
      - An extract from a letter written Oct. 1926 by F.T. Gates to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. dealing with pattern for electing Institute Boards, undated (Box 1)
  - 1927-1937 (Box 2)
    - Items of interest include: (Box 2)
      - Handwritten letter from William Welch to Raymond Fosdick on departure to Europe for study of institutions related to history of medicine, 1927 May 8 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence dealing with change of name of Avenue A in view of land purchase by Society of New York Hospital, 1927 December 28 (Box 2)
      - From Simon Flexner to Raymond Fosdick a list of items to be presented to Trustees for appropriations including developments in Plant and Animal Pathology at Princeton, 1929 February 18 (Box 2)
      - Copy of letter from John D. Rockefeller, Jr. to William Welch on his naming as President of the Board of Trustees and acknowledgement of thanks for gift of block South of 64th Street, 1929 November 20 (Box 2)
      - Handwritten draft by Thomas Debevoise of resolution regarding closing of streets in accordance with agreement with City in consideration of Mr. Rockefeller's gift of property known as Billings Estate, 1930 October 29 (Box 2)
      - Handwritten letter from Eugene L. Opie to Raymond Fosdick regretting he could not attend memorial service for L.G. Myers, 1932 February 1 (Box 2)
      - Signed amendment with eleven affected members for changes in Rules Governing Retiring Allowances, 1934 February (Box 2)
      - Group of letters dating back to Oct. 31, 1916 reviewing and reopening question of depreciation, allowances, 1934 June 15 (Box 2)
      - Letter from Edric B. Smith to Simon Flexner listing gifts made to Institute by the Rockefeller. Foundation 1915-1917, 1934 June 25 (Box 2)
      - Letter from John D. Rockefeller, Jr; deeding property bounded by 67th-68th Streets and First and York Avenues to Rockefeller Institute which is to be transferred to Memorial Hospital, if within five years Memorial Hospital is financially in a position to use the land., 1934 September 25 (Box 2)
      - Letter from Henry James to Raymond Fosdick regarding additional honorarium for Simon Flexner in his retirement, 1935 October 3 (Box 2)
      - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. 'S copy of remarks he made on the occasion of Simon Flexner's retirement and election of Herbert S. Gasser as Director of the Rockefeller Institute, 1935 October 7 (Box 2)
      - Simon Flexner letters of resignation as Director of the Institute and member of the Board of Trustees, 1935 October 4 1935 October 17 (Box 2)
      - Comments by Henry James pointing out there is no need for Trustees to ratify each and every action of Finance Committee. Trustees need only to be informed of actions for fiscal year, 1936 September 30 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence from July 5, 1934 regarding Van Heusen Estate, 1936 November 18 (Box 2)
      - Copy of letter from Rockefeller Foundation concerning change in policy regarding capital gifts, 1937 May 12 (Box 2)
  - 1938-1955 (Box 3)
    - Items of interest include: (Box 3)
      - Copy of Promise and Agreement between City of New York and Rockefeller Institute in construction of tunnel under East River Drive, 1939 October (Box 3)
      - Correspondence between John D. Rockefeller Jr. and Dr. Gasser regarding illness of Judge Appleton and election of David Rockefeller to Board of Trustees, 1940 September 9 1940 September 12 1940 September 16 (Box 3)
      - Draft of resolution that Institute not accept $ 25,000 grant from National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, 1940 October 25 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence dealing with insurance considered because of war risks, 1942 July (Box 3)
      - Various resignations, appointments and proxies dealing with the merger of the two Boards and planned reorganization, 1953 May-June (Box 3)
      - Letter from John D. Rockefeller, Jr. to David Rockefeller consenting to new By-Laws for Corporation (Box 3)
      - Circulated votes on appointment, salary and leave of absence for Haldan Keffer Hartline and Frank Brink, Jr., 1953 July 17 (Box 3)
      - Waiver of notice of meeting to amend Charter to make Institute part of University of State of New York and power to grant degrees, 1954 October 15 (Box 3)
      - Invitation and Program for 50th Anniversary Convocation (Box 3)
      - Signed approvals of Executive Committee for action to be taken regarding Rudolph Winterberg Estate, 1955 May 4 (Box 3)
      - Signed proxies for meeting to amend By-Laws (Art. XV: Budget), 1955 June 27 (Box 3)
      - Copy of correspondence regarding bill of William M. Ellard for survey and Analysis 66th-67th-Street and York Avenues, 1955 June 28 (Box 3)
      - Preliminary memo prepared by Debevoise, Plimpton and McLean on proposed York Ave. Redevelopment Project, 1955 July 9 (Box 3)
      - Signed proxies to amend Art. VI and Art. X and repeal Art. XI (Officers, Vice-President, Directors), 1955 August 15 (Box 3)
      - Two letters dealing with real estate on the West side of York Avenue., 1957 September 6 1959 February 4 (Box 3)
  - 1910-1956 (Box 4)
    - Notices of meetings of Board of Trustees, Corporation or Committees and signed proxies., 1910-1936; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Dockets of meetings, 1924-1938 1939-1950 1951-1956 (Box 4)
    - Secretary's Exhibit Book, 3 folders and 2 envelopes (Box 4)
      Arrangement
      Arranged chronologically (as per minutes).
      Special items as follows:.
      - Items of interest include:
        - Photographic copy of engrossed memorial to Frederick Taylor Gates, 1929 February 6[?] (Box 4)
        - Original minutes on occasion of William H. Welch resignation from Board of Trustees. Signed by Raymond B. Fosdick, Henry James, Simon Flexner, 1933 October 27 (Box 4)
        - Photographic copy of engrossed memorial to John Davison Rockefeller, 1937 May 23 (Box 4)
    - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondence, 1934-1950 (Box 4)
      Letter (copy) November 7, 1934 from Janet Warfield, secretary, acknowledging October 23, 1934 letter (copy) from Simon Flexner in appreciation of gift of the parcel of land bounded by 67th-68th Streets, York Avenue and 1st and calling attention to letter (copy) written by William Welch, November 15, 1929 in appreciation of gift of land 63rd-64th Streets, York and East River and acceptance of Corporation presidency.
      Letter (copy) April 24, 1950 from H.S. Gasser to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. on his request that he not be renominated for Presidency of Board of Trustees. October 27, 1950 letter (copy) sent to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. from Board of Trustees on his retirement as President and excerpt from Board of Trustees Minutes October 27, 1950 with copy of John D. Rockefeller's letter to H.S. Gasser of April 17, 1950.
- Edric B. Smith, 1943-1953; 1 box (2 1/2 inches) (Box 5)
  This collection is an addition to RG 130.6 (3) and is for the period 1943 June to April 1953. Any user should note the gap from July 1942 to May 1953.
  Consists of correspondence between members of the Board of Trustees and the secretary of the Board, Edric B. Smith. Deals with the business of the Board, including retirements, budget approvals, expenditure approvals, building remodeling, integration of Princeton and New York City laboratories, and elections to the Board. Correspondence with Thomas Debevoise deals with approvals of form and content of the Minutes of Board meetings. Also included are copies of signed approvals of certain actions taken by the Board.
  Arranged in chronological order: 1943 June-November 1947; 1948 January-November 1950; 1951 January-April 1953.
  - Items of interest include:
    - Action taken by Trustees to consider Integration of Princeton and New York City laboratories, 1947 May 2 (Box 5)
    - Agreement to accept 70% settlement on loss of principle in a remainder interest under the will of Edith A. Cohen, 1947 November 18 (Box 5)
    - Letter to H.S. Gasser from J.D. Rockefeller, Jr. with details of a 13-year Trust Fund providing income for The RIMR (copy), 1948 June 16 (Box 5)
    - John D. Rockefeller approval for proceeding with Hospital construction despite high cost, (copy), 1949 February 9 (Box 5)
    - Copy of Dr. Gasser's Minute at decision of John D. Rockefeller, Jr. decision not to stand for reelection as President of the Board of Trustees, 1950 October (Box 5)
    - From John D. Rockefeller, Jr. to Members of Corporation acknowledging Minute expressing appreciation of his role in RI history, 1951 January 19; (multigraph copy) (Box 5)
    - Approval for additional annuities for employees retired before benefits from Social Security established, 1951 June 29 (Box 5)